The Tesseract has awakened.
It is on a neutral world, a human world.
They wield its power,
but our ally knows it's working,
so that they never will learn.
He's ready to lead, and our force,
our Chitauri will follow.
The world will be his and the universe yours.
And the humans, what can they do, but burn.
How bad is it?
That's the problem, sir. We don't know.
Dr. Selvig read an energy surge from
the Tesseract four hours ago.
NASA didn't authorize Selvig to
pull the test phase.
He wasn't testing it, he wasn't even in the room.
Spontaneous advancement
It just turned itself on?
What are the engine levels now?
Climbing. When Selvig couldn't
shut it down, we ordered the evac.
How long to get everyone out?
Campus should be clear in the next half hour.
Do better.
Sir, evacuation maybe futile.
We should tell them to go back to sleep?
If we can't control the Tesseract's energy,
there may not be a minimum safe distance.
I need you to make sure that phase
2 prototypes are shipped out.
Sir, is that really a priority right now?
Until such time as the world ends,
we will act as though it intends to spin on.
Clear out the tech below. Every piece
of phase two on a truck and gone.
Yes, sir. Come with me.
Talk to me,  Doctor.
Director.
Is there anything we know for certain?
- Tesseract is misbehaving.
- Is that supposed to be funny?
No, it's not funny at all.
The Tesseract is not only active,
she's...misbehaving.
How soon until you pull the plug?
She's an energy source.
If we turn off the power, she turns it back on.
-  If she reaches peak level...
- We've prepared for this, doctor.
- Harnessing energy from space.
- We don't have the harness.
Our calculations are far from complete.
Now she's throwing off interference, radiation
Nothing harmful,
low levels of gamma radiation.
That can be harmful.
Where's Agent Barton?
The Hawk?  Up in his nest, as usual.
Agent Barton, report to me.
I gave you this detail so you could
keep a close eye on things.
- I can see better from a distance.
- Are you seeing anything that might
- set this thing off?
- Doctor, it's spiking again.
No one come or gone.
It's oven is clean.
No contacts, no I.M.'s.
If there was any tampering, sir.
It wasn't at this end.
- At this end?
- Yes, a cube of space, one end of the door.
Yeah, the cube is a doorway to the other end of space, right?
The doors open from both sides.
Sir, please put down the spear!
You have a heart.
Please don't.
- I still need that.
- This doesn't have to get any messier.
Of course it does.
I've come too far for anything else.
I am Loki of Asgard,
- and I am burdened with glorious purpose.
- Loki, brother of Thor?
We have no quarrel with your people.
An ant has no quarrel with a boot.
- You planning to step on us?
- I come with glad tidings,
- of a world made free.
- Free from what?
Freedom. Freedom is life's great lie.
Once you accept that, in your heart...
You will know peace.
Yeah, you say peace, I kind of
think you mean the other piece.
Sir, Director Fury is stalling.
This place is about to blow
Drop a hundred feet of raw material,
he means to bury us.
- Like The Pharaohs of Odin.
- He was right.
The portal is collapsing in on itself.
You got maybe two minutes
before this goes critical.
Drop him.
Need these vehicles.
- Who's that?
- He didn't tell me.
Hill, do you copy? Barton is....
He's got the Tesseract! Track it down!
ets go, no no no.. leave leave, go.
We cleared upstairs, sir.
We need to go.
Director? Director Fury , do you copy?
The Tesseract is with the hostile force.
I have men down. Hill?
A lot of men still under,
don't know how many survivors.
Sound the general call,
I want every living soul not needing rescue
- looking for that briefcase.
- Roger that.
Coulson, get back to base.
This is a level seven.
As of right now, we are at war.
What do we do?
I do not want to end tonight.
I want to know how
for it to end.
Believe me, you must
to be better prepared.
Do you work?
Lermentoville?
Is he confident that we will do -
transport without him?
I thought that a General
Tchalakov handle exports.
Tchalakov. Running Boy, doll.
Outdated information
derived from the fall.
Famous Black Widow
it's just a pretty face.
Do I feel beautiful?
We do not need Lermentovia
transport tank.
Tell him that we give up
medium term by hand. It's true ...
You may have to write it down.
Yes?
You ask.
- Listen carefully ...
- Silenskin box 114, the third floor.
F-22 close to you 13 draw
kilometer radius.
Put the woman on the phone,
or I will blow up the block
before you can make the lobby.
- We need you to come in.
- Are you kidding? I'm working!
- This takes precedence.
- I'm in the middle of an interrogation and this
moron is giving me everything.
I don't give everything.
- Look, you can't pull me out
of this right now. - Natasha.
Barton's been compromised.
Let me put you on hold.
- Where's Barton now?
- We don't know.
- But he's alive.
- We think so.
I'll brief you on everything when you get back.
But first, we need you to talk to the big guy.
Coulson, you know that Stark trusts
me about as far as he can throw me.
No, I've got Stark.
You get the big guy.
Oh, God.
- Do not come here!
- Who are you?
Go away. Here is a disease.
Are you a doctor?
My father did not wake up!
Body heat, and he
make noise, but did not open his eyes.
A slower rate.
My father ...
And when they?
Please...
Should have got paid up front, Banner.
You know, for a man who's
supposed to be avoiding stress,
you picked a hell of a place to settle.
- Avoiding stress isn't the secret.
-Then what is it? Yoga?
ou brought me to the edge of the city, smart.
I uh...assume the whole place is surrounded?
Just you and me.
And your actress buddy, is she a spy too?
Do you start that young?
- I did.
- Who are you?
Natasha Romanoff.
Are you here to kill me, Miss Romanoff?
Because that's not gonna
work out for everyone.
No. No. Of course not.
I'm here on behalf of SHIELD.
SHIELD. How did they find me?
We never lost you, doctor.
We've kept our distance,
even helped keep some
other interested parties off your scent.
- Why?
- Nick Fury seems to trust you.
But now I need you to come in.
- What if I say no?
- I'll persuade you.
And what if the...other guy says no?
You've been more than a
year without an incident.
I don't think you wanna break that streak.
I don't get every time what I want.
Doctor, we're facing a
potential global catastrophe.
- Well, those I actively try to avoid.
- This is the
Tesseract.
It has the potential energy
to wipe out the planet.
What does Fury want me to do? Swallow it?
Well, he wants you to find it. It's been taken.
It omits a gamma signature
that's too weak for us to trace.
There's no one that knows
gamma radiation like you do.
If there was, that's where I'd be.
- So Fury isn't after the monster?
- Not that he's told me.
And he tells you everything?
- Talk to Fury, he needs you on this.
- He needs me in a cage?
- No one's gonna put you in a...
- Stop lying to me!
I'm sorry, that was mean.
I just wanted to see what you'd do.
Why don't we do this the easy way,
where you don't use that,
and the other guy doesn't
make a mess? Okay?
Natasha.
Stand down. We're good here.
Just you and me?
This is out of line, Director.
You're dealing with
forces you can't control.
You ever been in a war,
Councilman? In a firefight?
Did you feel an over abundance of control?
You saying that this Asgard has
declared war on our planet?
Not Asgard. Loki.
He can't be working alone.
What about the other one? His brother.
Our intelligence says, Thor is not a hostile.
But he's worlds away,
we can't depend on him to help either.
It's up to us.
Which is why you should
be focusing on phase two,
- it was designed for exactly...
- Phase two isn't ready, our enemy is.
- We need a response team.
- The Avengers Initiative was shut down.
- This isn't about The Avengers.
- We have seen the list.
We're running the world's greatest
covert security network
and you're gonna leave the fate of
human race to a handful of freaks.
I'm not leaving anything to anyone.
We need a response team.
These people may be isolated,
unbalanced even,
but I believe with the right push
they can be exactly what we need.
- You believe?
- War isn't won by sentiment, Director.
No, it's won by soldiers.
There's not enough time. I'm gotta
pull into the water.
- You wont be alone.
- .Oh God.
This guy is still alive.
Trouble sleeping?
I slept for 70 years, Sir.
I think I've had my fill.
Then you should be out,
celebrating, seeing the world.
I went under, the world was at war,
I wake up, they say we won.
They didn't say what we lost.
We've made some mistakes along the way.
Some very recently.
- You here with a mission, sir?
- I am.
- Trying to get me back in the world?
- Trying to save it.
Hydra's secret weapon.
Howard Stark fished that out of the ocean
when he was looking for you.
He thought what we think,
the Tesseract could be the key to
unlimited sustainable energy.
That's something the world sorely needs.
- Who took it from you?
- He's called Loki.
He's not from around here.
There's a lot we'll have to bring
you up to speed on if you're in.
The world has gotten even
stranger than you already know.
At this point, I doubt
anything would surprise me.
Ten bucks says you're wrong.
There's a debriefing package waiting
for you back at your apartment.
Is there anything you can tell us about...
...the Tesseract that we ought to know now?
You should have left it in the ocean.
You're good to go on this end.
The rest is up to you.
You disconnected the transition lines?
Are we off the grid?
Stark Towers is about to become a
beacon of self sustaining clean energy.
Wow, so maybe our reactor takes over
and it actually works?
I assume. Light her up.
- How does it look?
- Like Christmas, but with more...me.
Gotta go wider on the public
awareness campaign.
You need to do some press.
I can do some more tomorrow,
I'm working on the zoning
for the next billboards.
Pepper, you're killing me. Remember?
Enjoy the moment.
I remember.
Sir, Agent Coulson of SHIELD is on the line.
I'm not in. I'm actually out.
Sir, I'm afraid he's insisting.
Close the line Jarvis. I got a date.
Levels are holding steady...I think.
Of course they are,
I was directly involved.
Which brings me to my next question.
How does it feel to be a genius?
Well, ha, I really wouldn't
know now, would I?
What do you mean?
All this, came from you.
No. All this, came from that.
Give yourself some credit, please.
Stark Tower...
...is your baby. Give yourself,
twelve percent of the credit.
- Twelve percent?
- An argument can be made for fifteen.
- Twelve percent for my baby?
- Well, I did do all the heavy lifting.
Literally, I lifted the heavy things.
And sorry, but the security snafu?
That was on you.
- My private elevator.
- You mean our elevator?
It was teeming with sweaty workmen.
I'm going to pay for that
comment about percentages
in some subtle way later on, aren't I?
Not gonna be that subtle.
I'll tell you what. Next building
is gonna say 'Potts' on the tower.
- On the lease.
- Call your mom, can you bunk over?
Sir, the telephone. I'm afraid
my protocol's are being overwritten.
Stark, we need to talk.
You have reached the life model
decoy of Tony Stark,
please leave a message.
- This is urgent.
- Then leave it urgently.
- Security breach. That's on you.
- Mr Stark.
- Phil! Come in.
- Phil.
- I can't stay.
- Uh...his first name is Agent.
Come on in, we're celebrating.
Which is why he can't stay.
Soon as possible.
I don't like being handed things
That's alright, cause
I love to be handed things.
So, let's trade.
Thank you.
Official consulting hours are between
eight and five every other Thursday.
- This isn't a consultation.
- Is this about The Avengers?
Which I...I know nothing about.
The Avengers Initiative
was scrapped, I thought.
- And I didn't even qualify.
- I didn't know that either.
Yeah, apparently I'm volatile,
self obsessed,
don't play well with others.
That I did know.
- This isn't about personality profiles anymore.
- Whatever.
Miss Potts, got a sec?
You know, I thought we were having a moment.
I was having twelve percent of a moment.
This seems so serious,
Phil's pretty shaken.
- How did you notice? Why is he Phil?
- What is all this?
This is uh...
This.
- I'm going to take the jet to D.C. tonight.
- Tomorrow.
You have homework.
You have a lot of homework.
Well, what if I didn't?
If you didn't?
You mean if you finished?
Then ...
Square deal. It's the last date.
Work hard.
- Do you drive past the airport, by chance?
- I can drop you.
Oh, fantastic. Does the cellist
You? Is it true relationship?
- He moved back to Portland.
- What?
We are a forty-minute
from the base, sir.
So this Dr. Banner was trying to replicate
the serum that was used on me?
A lot of people were.
You were the world's first superhero.
Banner thought gammer radiation might
hold the key to unlocking
Erskine's original formula.
- Didn't really go his way, did it?
- Not so much.
When he's got that thing though,
guy's like a Stephen Hawking.
He's like a smart person.
I gotta say, it's an honor
to meet you, officially.
I sort of met you, I mean,
I watched you while you were sleeping.
I mean, I was...I was present while you
were unconscious from the ice.
You know, it's really, it's just a...just
a huge honor to have you on board.
- Well, I hope I'm the man for the job.
- Oh, you are. Absolutely.
Uh...we've made some modifications
to the uniform. I had a little design input.
The uniform? Aren't the stars
and stripes a little...old fashioned?
Everything that's happening, the
things that are about to come to light,
people might just need a little old fashioned.
- The Chitauri grow restless.
- Let them grow restless.
- I will lead them in the glorious battle.
- Battle? Against a meagre might of earth?
- Glorious, not lengthy.
If your force is as formidable as you claim.
You question us?
Question him?
He who put the scepter in your hand?
Who gave you ancient
knowledge and new purpose?
When you were cast out, defeated!
I was a king! The rightful king
of Asgard. Betrayed.
Your ambition is little and full of childish need.
We look beyond the earth to great worlds
The Tesseract will avail.
You don't have the Tesseract yet.
I don't threaten.
But until I open the doors,
until your force is mine to
command, you are the wars.
You will have your war as guardian.
If you fail,
if the Tesseract is kept from us,
there will be no realm, no barren moon,
no crevasse where I can't find you.
You think you know pain?
You will receive something sweet as pain.
- Get your captain equipment.
- All right.
Agent Romanoff , he's Captain Rogers.
- They need you on the bridge.
- See you there.
There was quite the buzz
around here, finding you in the ice.
I thought Coulson was gonna swoon.
Did he ask you to sign his
Captain America trading cards yet?
- Trading Cards?
- They're vintage, he's very proud.
Dr. Banner.
Oh, yeah. Hi.
- They told me you'd be coming.
- Word is you can find the cube.
- Is that the only word on me?
- Only word I care about.
Must be strange for you, all of this.
Well, this is actually kind of familiar.
Gentlemen, you may wanna
step inside in a minute.
It's gonna get a little hard to breath.
Is this is a submarine?
Really? They wanted me in a submerged
pressurized metal container?
Oh, no. This is much worse.
- All engine operating.
SHEILD emergency
protocol, 1 9 3.6 in effect.
- We're in, sir.
- Good.
- Lets vanish.
- Engage retro reflection panels.
- Reflection panels engaged.
- Gentlemen.
- Doctor, thank you for coming.
- Thanks for asking nicely.
So, uh...how long am I staying?
Once we get our hands on the
Tesseract, you're in the clear.
Where are you with that?
We're sweeping every
wirelessly accessible camera on the planet.
Cell phones, laptops.
If it's connected to a satellite,
-  it's eyes and ears for us.
- That's still not gonna find them in time.
You have to narrow the field.
How many spectrometers
do you have access to?
- How many are there?
- Call every lab you know,
tell them to put the
spectrometers on the roof
and calibrate them for gamma rays.
I'll rough out a tracking algorithm
based on cluster recognition.
At least we could rule out a few places.
- Do you have somewhere for me to work?
- Agent Romanoff,
would you show Dr. Banner
to his laboratory, please.
You're gonna love it, Doc. We got all the toys.
Put over there.
- Is this the stuff you need?
- Yeah, Iridium.
It's found in meteorites, it forms anti-protons.
- It's very hard to get hold of
- Specially if SHIELD knows you need it.
Well, I didn't know!
The Tesseract is showing me so much.
It's...it's more than knowledge, it's truth.
I know. What did it show you,
Agent Barton?
- My next target.
- Tell me what you need.
I need a distraction.
And an eyeball.
I mean, if it's not too much trouble.
No, no. It's fine.
It's a vintage set.
It took me a couple of
years to collect them all.
Near mint, slight foxing
around the edges, but...
We got a hit. Sixty seven percent match.
Weight, cross match, seventy nine percent.
Location?
Stuttgart, Germany.
28, Canning Strasse.
- He's not exactly hiding.
- Captain,
you're up.
Kneel before me.
I said.
Kneel!
Is not this simpler?
Is this not your natural state?
It's the unspoken truth of humanity,
that you crave subjugation.
The bright lure of freedom diminishes
your life's joy in a mad scramble for power,
and identity.
You were made to be ruled.
In the end, you will always kneel.
Not to men like you.
- There are no men like me.
- There are always men like you.
Look to your elder, people.
Let him be an example.
You know, the last time I was in Germany
and saw a man standing
above everybody else,
we ended up disagreeing.
I'm not the one who's out of time.
Loki, drop the weapon and stand down.
Kneel.
Not today!
The guy's all over the place.
Agent Romanoff, did you miss me?
Make your move, Reindeer names.
Good move.
- Mr Stark.
- Captain.
- Didn't he say anything?
- Not a word.
Just get in here.
We're low on time.
I don't like it.
What? Rock of Ages
giving up so easily?
I don't remember it being that easy.
This guy packs a wallop.
Still, you were pretty spry,
for an older fellow.
- What's your thing? Pilates?
- What?
It's like calisthenics.
You might have missed a couple things,
you know, doing time as a Capsicle.
Fury didn't tell me he was calling you in.
Yeah, there's a lot of
things Fury doesn't tell you.
Where's this coming from?
What's the matter? Scared of a little lightning?
I'm not overly fond of what follows.
- Now there's that guy.
- Another Asgardian?
- Think the guy's a friendly?
- Doesn't matter.
If he frees Loki or kills him,
the Tesseract's lost.
- Stark, we need a plan of attack.
- I have a plan. Attack.
- I'd sit this one out, Cap.
- I don't see how I can.
These guys come from legends,
they're basically Gods.
There's only one God, ma'am.
And I'm pretty sure he doesn't dress like that.
- Where's the Tesseract?
- I missed you too.
- Do I look to be in a gaming mood?
- Oh, you should thank me.
With the Bifrost gone,
how much dark energy did the
All-Father have to muster
to conjure you here?
Your precious earth.
I thought you dead.
Our father...
- Your father.
He did tell you my true parentage, did he not?
We were raised together.
We played together, we fought together.
- Do you remember none of that?
- I remember a shadows.
living in the shade of your greatness.
I remember you tossing me into an abyss.
I who was and should be king!
So you take the world I love as
recompense for your imagined slights?
No, the earth is under my protection, Loki.
And you're doing a marvelous job with that.
The humans slaughter each other in
droves, while you ideally threat.
I mean to rule them.
That's why should I not...
Think yourself above them.
Well, yes.
Then you miss the truth of ruling, brother.
A throne would suit you ill.
I've seen worlds you've never known about.
I have grown, Odin's son, in my exile.
I have seen the true power of the Tesseract.
And when I wield it...
Who showed you this power?
Who controls the would be king?
- I am the king!
- Not here!
You give up the Tesseract!
You give up this poisonous dream!
You come home.
I do not have it.
You need the cube to bring me home,
but I've sent it off. I know not where.
You listen well, brother.
I'm listening.
- Do not touch me again.
- Then don't take my stuff.
You have no idea what you're dealing with.
Uh...Shakespeare in the park.
Doth mother know, you weareth her drapes?
This is beyond you, metal man.
Loki will face Asgardian justice.
He gives up the cube and he's all yours.
Until then,
...stay out of the way.
Tourist.
Okay.
How about that.
That's enough!
Now, I don't know what you plan on doing here.
I've come here to put
and end to Loki's schemes!
Then prove it. Put that hammer down.
Uh...yep! No! Bad call!
He loves his hammer!
You want me to put the hammer down?
Are we done here?
In case it's unclear, you try to escape,
you so much as scratch that glass.
Thirty thousand feet,
straight down in a steel trap.
You get how that works?
Ant.
Boot.
It's an impressive cage.
Not built, I think, for me.
Built for something a lot stronger than you.
Oh, I've heard.
The mindless beast, makes play to be the man.
How desperate are you?
You call on these lost
creatures to defend you.
How desperate am I?
You threaten my world with war.
You steal a force you can't hope to control.
You talk about peace and you kill
cause it's fun.
You have made me very desperate.
You might not be glad that you did.
Ooh. It burns you to come so close.
To have the Tesseract,
to have power, unlimited power.
And for what?
A world for all mankind to share,
and then to be reminded what real power is.
Well let me know if real power...
...will want some magazine or something.
- He really grows on you, doesn't he?
- Loki's gonna drag this out.
- So, Thor, what's his play?
- He has an army called the Chitauri,
that none of Asgard nor any world know.
He means to lead them against your people.
They will win him the earth.
- Return, I suspect, for the Tesseract.
- An army,
- from outer space.
- So he's building another portal.
- That's what he needs Erik Selvig for.
- Selvig?
- He's an astrophysicist.
- He's a friend.
Loki has him under some kind of spell,
- along with one of ours.
- I wanna know why Loki let us take him.
- He's not leading an army from here.
- I don't think we should be focusing on Loki.
That guy's brain is a bag full of cats,
you could smell crazy on him.
I don't care how you speak.
Loki is beyond reason,
but he is of Asgard, and he's my brother.
He killed eighty people in two days.
- He's adopted.
- I think its about the mechanics.
- Iridium, what did they need the Iridium for?
- It's a stabilizing agent.
Means the portal won't collapse
on itself, like it did at SHIELD.
No hard feelings Point Break,
you've got a mean swing.
Also, it means the portal can open as wide,
and stay open as long, as Loki wants.
That man is playing gallaga.
Thought we wouldn't notice, but we did.
- How does Fury even see these?
- He turns.
Sounds exhausting.
The rest of the raw materials, Agent Barton
can get his hands on pretty easily.
Only major component he
still needs is a power source.
A high energy density,
something to kick start the cube.
When did you become an expert in
thermonuclear astrophysics?
Last night.
The packet, Selvig's notes,
the Extraction Theory papers.
Am I the only one who did the reading?
Does Loki need any particular
kind of power source?
He got to heat the cube to a hundred
and twenty million Kelvin
just to break through the Coulomb barrier.
Unless, Selvig has figured out how to
stabilize the quantum tunnelling effect.
Well, if he could do that he could achieve
Heavy Ion Fusion at any reactor on the planet.
Finally, someone who speaks English.
- Is that what just happened?
- It's good to meet you, Dr. Banner.
You're work on anti-electron
collisions is unparalleled.
And I'm a huge fan of the way you lose control
and turn into an enormous green rage monster.
- Thanks.
- Dr. Banner is only here to track the cube.
- I was hoping you might join him.
- Let's start with that stick of his
It may be magical, but it works an
awful lot like a Hydra weapon.
I don't know about that,
but it is powered by the cube.
And I'd like to know how Loki used it to turn
two of the sharpest men I know
into his personal flying monkeys.
- Monkeys? I do not understand.
- I do.
I understood that reference.
- Shall we play it, Doctor?
- This way, Sir.
The gamma readings are definitely consistent
with Selvig's reports on the Tesseract.
- But it's gonna take weeks to process.
- If we bypass their mainframe
and direct a reroute to the Homer cluster,
we can clock this around six hundred teraflops.
All I packed was a tooth brush.
You know, you should come
by Stark Towers sometime.
Top ten floors, all R and D.
- You'd love it, it's candy land.
- Thanks, but the last time I was in New York, I...
kind of broke Harlem.
Well, I promise a stress
free environment. No tension.
No surprises.
- Nothing?
- Are you nuts?
You really have got a lid on it,
haven't you? What's your secret?
Mellow jazz? Bongo drums? Huge bag of weed?
Is everything a joke to you?
Threatening the safety of everyone
on this ship isn't funny.
No offense, Doctor.
No, it....it's alright. I wouldn't
have come aboard if I couldn't
- handle pointy things.
- You're tiptoeing, big man.
You need to strut.
And you need to focus on
the problem, Mr. Stark.
You think I'm not?
Why did Fury call us and why now?
Why not before? What isn't he telling us.
I can't do the equation unless
I have all the variables.
- You think Fury's hiding something?
- He is a spy.
He's a spy. Captain, he's the spy.
His secrets have secrets.
It's bugging him too, isn't it?
- Uh, I just wanna finish my work here and...
- Doctor?
A world like for all mankind,
Loki's jab at Fury about the cube.
- I heard it.
- Well, I think that was meant for you.
Even if Barton didn't post
that all over the news.
The Stark Tower? That big ugly......,
building in New York?
It's powered by Stark Reactors,
self sustaining energy source.
That building will run itself
for what, a year?
That's just the prototype.
I'm kind of the only name in
clean energy right now.
So why didn't SHIELD bring him in
on the Tesseract project?
I should probably look into that once
my decryption programme
finishes breaking into all of SHIELD's secure files.
- I'm sorry, did you say.....?
- Jarvis has been running it since I hit the bridge.
In a few hours we'll know every dirty
secret SHIELD has ever tried to hide.
- Blueberry? - Yet you're confused about
why they didn't want you around?
An intelligence organization that fears intelligence?
Historically not possible.
I think Loki's trying to wind us up.
This is a man who means to start a war,
and if don't stay focused, he'll succeed.
We have orders, we should follow them.
Following is not really my style.
And you're all about style, aren't you?
Of the people in this room, which one is;
a-wearing a spangly outfit, and b- not of use?
Steve, tell me none of this smells
a little funky to you?
Just find the cube.
That's the guy my dad never shut up about?
Wondering if they shouldn't have kept him on ice.
The guy's not wrong about Loki,
he does have the jump on us.
What he's got is an acme dynamite kit.
It's gonna blow up in his face,
and I'm gonna be there when it does..
And I'll read all about it.
Or you'll be suiting up like the rest of us.
Ah, see. I don't get a suit of armor.
I'm exposed, like a nerve.
- It's a nightmare.
- You know, I've got a cluster of shrapnel,
trying every second to crawl its way into my heart.
This stops it. This little circle of light.
It's part of me now, not just armor.
- It's a terrible privilege.
- But you can control it.
- Because I learned how.
- It's different.
Hey, I've read all about your accident.
That much gammer exposure should have killed you.
So you're saying that the Hulk,
the other guy, saved my life?
That's nice.
It's a nice sentiment.
Save it for what?
I guess we'll find out.
- You may not enjoy that.
- You just might.
As soon as Loki took the doctor we moved Jane Foster.
We've got an excellent observatory in Traunsee.
She was asked to consult there
very suddenly yesterday.
Handsome fee, private plane, very remote.
- She'll be safe.
- Thank you.
It's no accident Loki taking Erik Selvig.
I dread what he plans for him once he's done.
- Erik is a good man.
- He talks about you a lot.
You changed his life.
- You changed everything around here.
- They were better as they were.
We pretend on Asgard that
we're more advanced, but we.
We come here battling like Bilchsteim.
- Like what?
- Bilchsteim. You know; huge, scaly, big antlers.
- You don't have those?
- I don't think so.
They are repulsive, and
they trample everything in their path.
When I first came to earth, Loki's rage followed me
here and your people paid the price.
And now again,
n my youth I courted war.
War hasn't started yet.
You think you can make Loki tell us what the Tesseract is?
I do not know. Loki's mind is far afield,
it's not just power he craves,
it's vengeance upon me.
There's no pain that would prise his need from him.
A lot of guys think that, until the pain stops.
- What are you asking me to do?
- I'm asking, what are you prepared to do?
Loki is a prisoner.
Then why do I feel like he's the only person on
this boat that wants to be here?
There's not many people that can sneak up on me.
But you figured I'd come after.
After whatever tortures Fury can concoct,
you would appear as a friend,
as a balm.
- And I would cooperate.
- I wanna know what you've done to Agent Barton.
I'd say I've expanded his mind.
And once you've won. Once you're king of the mountain.
What happens to his mind?
- Is this love, Agent Romanoff?
- Love is for children. I owe him a debt.
Tell me.
Before I worked for SHIELD, I
I made a name for myself.
I have a very specific skillset.
I didn't care who I used it for, or on.
I got on SHIELD's radar in a bad way.
Agent Barton was sent to kill me,
he made a different call.
And what will you do if I vow to spare him?
- I'll not let you out.
- Ah, no. But I like this
Your world in the balance, and you bargain for one man?
Regime's fall everyday.
I tend not to weep over that, I'm Russian,
Or I was.
- And what are you now?
- It's really not that complicated.
I've got red in my ledger, I'd like to wipe it out.
Can you?
Can you wipe out that much red?
Drakoff's daughter?
Sao Paulo?
The hospital file?
Barton told me everything.
Your ledger is dripping, it's gushing red,
and you think saving a man no more virtuous
than yourself will change anything?
This is the basest sentimentality.
This is a child at prayer.
Pathetic.
You lie and kill
in the service of liars and killers.
You pretend to be separate,
to have your own code,
something that makes up for the horrors.
But they are a part of you,
and they will never go away.
I won't barter Barton! Not until I make him kill you.
Slowly, intimately, in every way he knows you fear.
And then he'll wake just long enough to see his good work,
and when he screams I'll split his skull
This is my bargain, you mewling quin!
You're a monster.
Oh, no.
You brought the monster.
- So, Banner? That's your play?
- What?
Loki means to unleash the Hulk.
Keep Banner in the lab, I'm on my way.
Set the door locked.
Thank you, for your cooperation.
- What are you doing, Mr. Stark?
- kind of been wondering the same thing about you
You're supposed to be locating the Tesseract.
We are, the model's locked and we're
sweeping for the signature now.
When we get a hit, we'll have the
location within half a mile.
And you'll get your cube back, no muss, no fuss.
What is Phase 2?
Phase 2 is SHIELD used the cube to make weapons.
Sorry, the computer was moving a little slow for me.
Rogers, we gathered everything related
to the Tesseract.This does not...
- mean that we're.
- I'm sorry, Nick.
What were you lying?
- I was wrong, Director. The world hasn't changed a bit.
- Do you know about this?
You wanna think about removing yourself
from this environment, doctor?
I was in Calcutta, I was pretty well removed.
- Loki's manipulating you.
- And you've been doing what exactly?
You didn't come here because
I bat my eyelashes at you.
Yes, and I'm not leaving because
suddenly you get a little twitchy.
I'd like to know why SHIELD is using the Tesseract
to build weapons of mass destruction.
Because of him.
Me?
Last year earth had a visitor
from another planet
who had a grudge mass that levelled a small town.
We learned that not only are we not alone,
but we are hopelessly, hilariously
- out gunned.
- My people want nothing but peace with your planet.
But you're not the only people out there, are you?
And, you're not the only threat.
The world's filling up with people who can't be matched,
- they can't be controlled.
- Like you controlled the cube?
You're work with the Tesseract is
what drew Loki to it, and his allies.
It is the signal to all the realms that the
earth is ready for a higher form of war.
A higher form?
You forced our hand.
We had to come up with something.
A nuclear deterrent.
cause that always calms everything right down.
Remind me again how you made your fortune, Stark?
I'm sure if he still made weapons,
Stark would be neck deep...
Wait, Wait, Hold on. How is this now about me?
- I'm sorry, isn't everything?
- I thought humans were more evolved than this.
- Excuse me, did we come to your planet and blow stuff up?
- We can..
- You speak of control, yet you court chaos.
- It's his M.O., isn't it?
I mean, what are we, a team? No, no, no.
We're a chemical mixture that makes chaos.
We're...we're a time-bomb.
- You need to step away.
- Why shouldn't they guy let off a little steam?
- You know damn well why! Back off!
- Oh, I'm starting to want you to make me.
Yeah, big man in a suit of armor.
- Take that off, what are you?
- Genius, billionaire, playboy, philanthropist.
I know guys with none of that worth ten of you.
I've seen the footage.
The only thing you really fight for is yourself.
You're not the guy to make the sacrifice play,
to lay down on a wire and let the
other guy crawl over you.
I think I would just cut the wire.
Always a way out.
You know, you may not be a threat,
but you better stop pretending to be a hero
A hero, like you?
You're a laboratory experiment, Rogers.
Everything special about you came out of a bottle.
Put on the suite, let's go a few rounds.
- You people are so petty, and tiny.
- Yes, right.
Agent Romanoff, would you escort Dr.
Banner back to his...
Where? You're renting my room.
- The cell was just...
- In case you needed to kill me.
but you can't! I know, I tried.
I got low,
I didn't see an end, so I put a bullet in
my mouth and the other guy spit it out.
So I moved on, I focused on helping other people.
I was good until you dragged me back into this freak show.
and put everyone here at risk.
You wanna know my secret, Agent Romanoff?
You wanna know how I stay calm?
Dr. Banner.
put down the scepter.
Got it.
Sorry, kids. You don't get to see
my party trick after all.
Located the Tesseract?
- I can get there faster.
- The Tesseract belongs on Asgard,
- no human is a match for it.
- You're not going alone!
You gonna stop me?
Put on the suit, let's find out.
- I'm not afraid to hit an old man.
- Put on the suit.
Oh, my God.
- Put on the suit!
- Yep.
- Hill!
- Its a detonation. Number three engines is down.
-We're been hit.
-Fire engines.
- Talk to me.
- Turbine looks mostly intact, -
but it is impossible to get out there
and repair when we already there.
If we lose one of engine we wont be.
- Someone gonna get outside and patch the engine.
- Stark, did you capy that?
- I'm on it.
Okay.
You okay right?
Keep that engine down.
Attention.wait the cameras going dark.
Stay close.
Level four.
Engine three. I'll meet you there.
Doctor.
Bruce, you gotta fight.
This is just what Loki wants.
We're gonna be okay. Listen to me.
We're gonna be okay. Right?
I swear on my life I will get you out of this,
you will walk away, and never...
Your life?
Bruce.
We have been carrying 180 to the south.
Takes us to the water.
Free wind. Navigation
recalibration after the engine failure.
- Is the sun coming up?
- Yes sir.
Then put it on the left.
Takes us on the water.
One more turbine goes down
we're trapped.
Stark!
- Stark, I'm here!
- Good.
See what we got.
I gotta get this super conducting
cooling system back online
before I can access the rotors and work
on dislodging the debris.
I need you to get to that engine control panel
and tell me which relays are in overload position.
What's it look like in there?
It seems to run on some form of electricity.
Well, you're not wrong.
We're not your enemies, Banner.
Try to think.
The relays are intact.
- What's our next move?
- Even if I clear the rotors,
this thing won't re-engage without a jump.
I'm gonna have to get in there and push.
Well if that thing gets up to speed,
you'll get shredded.
Then stay in the control unit and reverse
polarity long enough to disengage mag..
Speak English.
See that red lever?
It'll slow the rotors down long
enough for me to get out.
Stand by it, wait for my word.
I need full evac on lower deck.
Grenade.
We gotta perimeter breach.
Hostile wiped SHIELD gear.
Hulk and Thor are in the research level
4, level 2 and 3.
Sir, the Hulk will tear this place apart!
- Get his attention.
- Escorts, Six o proceed to the.
- Don't get too close.
Target acquired.
Target engaged.
Target in moving.
Engine now all shut down.
Sir we lost all engine one.
It's Barton. He took out our system.
He's headed for the detention lab.
Does anybody copy?
This is Agent Romanoff.I copy.
- Stark,we losing altitude.
- I have noticed.
No!
Are you ever not going to fall for that?
The humans think us immortal. Should we test that?
Move away please.
Do you like this?
We started working on the prototype
after you sent The Destroyer.
Even I don't know what it does.
Do you wanna find out?
No!
Natasha ...
You're gonna lose.
Am I?
It's in your nature.
You're heroes are scattered,
your floating fortress falls from the sky.
- Where is my disadvantage?
- Your lack conviction.
I don't think I...
So that's what it does.
- Cap, need a lever.
- I need a minute here!
Lever, now!
I'm sorry, boss. They got rabbited.
Just stay awake. Eyes on me
- No, I'm clockin' out here
- Not an option.
It's okay, boss.
This was never gonna work if they
didn't have something to.....
Agent Coulson is down.
- The medical team on the way to the location.
- They're here.
These were in Phil Coulson's jacket.
Guess he never did get you to sign them.
We're dead in the air up here.
Our communications, location of the cube,
Banner, Thor. I got nothing for you.
Lost my one good eye.
Maybe I had that coming.
Yes.
We were going to build an arsenal with the Tesseract.
I never put all my chips on that number though,
because I was playing something even riskier.
There was an idea, Stark knows this,
called The Avengers Initiative.
The idea was to bring together
a group of remarkable people,
see if they could become something more.
See if they could work together when we needed them to,
to fight the battles that we never could.
Phil Coulson died still believing in that idea,
in heroes.
Well, it's an old fashioned notion.
You fell out of the sky.
- Did I hurt anybody?
- There's nobody around here to get hurt.
You did scare the hell out of some pigeons though.
- Lucky.
- Or just good aim.
You were awake when you fell.
- You saw?
- The whole thing, right through the ceiling.
Big and green and buck ass nude.
Here...
I didn't think those would fit you until
you shrunk down to a regular size fella.
Thank you.
- Are you an alien?
- What?
- From outer space, an alien?
- No.
Well then, son. You've got a condition.
Clint, You're gonna be alright.
You know that? Is that what you know?
I got...I gotta go in though.
I gotta flush him out.
We don't have that long, it's gonna take time.
I don't understand.
Have you ever had someone take your brain and play?
Pull you out and send something else in?
Do you know what it's like to be unmade?
You know that I do.
Why am I back? How did you get him out?
Cognitive recalibration.
I hit you really hard in the head.
Thanks.
Natasha,
- how many agents?
- Don't. Don't do that to yourself, Clint.
This is Loki.
This is monsters and magic and
nothing we were ever trained for.
- Loki, he got away?
- Yeah. I don't suppose you know where?
I didn't need to know. I didn't ask.
He's gonna make his play soon though. Today.
- We gotta stop him.
- Yeah? Who's we?
I don't know. Who's ever left.
Well, if I put an arrow in Loki's eye socket,
I'd sleep better I suppose.
Now you sound like you.
But you don't.
You're a spy, not a soldier.
Now you want to wade into a war. Why?
What did Loki do to you?
He didn't, I just...
Natasha.
I've been compromised.
I got red in my ledger,
I'd like to wipe it out.
- Was he married?
- No
He was a...cellist, I think.
I'm sorry. He seemed like a good man.
- He was an idiot.
- Why? For believing?
- For taking on Loki alone.
- He was doing his job.
He was out of his league.
He should have waited.
He should have...
- Sometimes there isn't a way out, Tony.
- Right. How did that work for him?
- Is this the first time you've lost a soldier?
- We're not soldiers!
- I'm not marching to Fury's fife.
- Neither am I.
He's got the same blood on his hands that Loki does,
but right now we gotta put
that behind us and get this done.
Now Loki needs a power source,
- if we can put together a list...
- He made it personal.
- That's not the point.
- That is the point. That's Loki's point.
- He hit us all right where we live. Why?
- To tear us apart.
He had to conquer his greed,
but he knows he has to take us out to win, right?
That's what he wants. He wants to beat us,
he wants to be seen doing it.
- He wants an audience.
- Right. I caught his act in Stuttgart.
Yeah. That's just previews, this is...
this is opening night. And Loki, he's a full-tail diva.
He wants flowers, he wants parades,
he wants a monument built to
the skies with his name plastered.
I hope that would be true.
- Time to go.
- Go where?
I'll tell you on the way. Can you fly one of those jets?
I can.
You got a suit? Yeah.
Then suit up.
- You guys aren't authorized to be in here.
- Son, just don't.
Sir.
Done is jacket.
They needed to push.
They found it. Get our communications back up
whatever you have to do.
- I want eyes on everything.
- Yes sir.
This device has already self sustainig.
- Shut it down, Dr. Selvig.
- It's too late.
It can't stop now.
He wants to show us something!
- A new universe.
- Okay.
The barrier is pure energy. It's unbreachable.
Yeah I get that.
Plan B.
Sir, mark 7 is not ready for deployment.
Then skip the spinning ring.We're run out of clock.
Please tell me you're going to
appeal to my humanity.
- Uh...actually, I'm planning to threaten.
- You should have left your armor on for that.
Yeah, it's seen a bit of mileage.
You've got the blue stick of destiny.
- Stalling me won't change anything.
- No, no, no! Threatening.
The Chitauri are coming, nothing will change that.
- What have I to fear?
- The Avengers.
It's what we call ourselves, sort of like a team.
Earth's Mightiest Heroes type of thing.
Yes, I've met them.
Yeah, takes us a while to get any traction,
I'll give you that one.
But, let's do a head count here.
Your brother, the demi-God
a super soldier, a living legend
who kind of lives up to the legend
a man with breath-taking anger management issues
a couple of master assassins, and you, big fella
you've managed to piss off every single one of them.
- That was the plan.
- Not a great plan.
When they come, and they will, they'll come for you.
- I have an army.
- We have a Hulk.
-I thought the beast had wandered off.
-You're missing the point. There's no throne,
there is no version of this, where you come out on top.
Maybe your army comes and
maybe it's too much for us, but it's all on you.
Because if we can't protect the Earth,
you can be damned well sure we'll avenge it.
How will your friends have time for me,
when they're so busy fighting you?
- It should work!
- Well, performance issues. You know?
Jarvis, anytime now.
- You will all fall before me.
And there's one other person you pissed off!
His name is Phil.
Right.
Army.
Loki, turn off the Tesseract or I'll destroy it!
You can't.
There is no stopping it.
- There is only the war!
- So be it.
- Stark, we're heading north east.
- What, did you stop for drive-through?
Swing that park, I'm gonna lay them out for you.
- So we have more incoming.
- Lets keep them occupied.
- Nat.
- Did you see them?
We need back up there.
- Stark, are you seeing this?
- I'm seeing, still working on believing..
- Where's Banner? Has he shown up yet?
- Banner?
Just keep me posted.
Jarvis, find me a soft spot.
Look at this. Look around you.
You think this madness will end with your rule?
It's too late. It's too late to stop it.
No. We can, together.
Sentiment!
You got civilian trap in the roof.
Loki.
There more down there.
- We got this. Go Go.
- You think you can hold them off?
Captain,
it would be my genuine pleasure.
Just like Budapest all over again!
You and I remember Budapest very differently.
National guard?
Does the army know what's happening here?
Do we?
I need men in these buildings.
There are people inside that
can run into the line of fire.
You take them through the
basement or through the subway,
you keep them off the streets.
- I need a perimeter as far back as 39th.
- Why the hell should I take orders from you?
I need men in those buildings,
lead the people down and away from the streets
I wanna shut off the perimeter
all the way down of 39 Street.
Well, we got its attention.
Where it heads to?
- Lets Thor hear what says.
- The powers surrounding the cube is impenetrable
Thor is right, we gotta deal with these guys.
- How do we do this? As a team.
- I have unfinished business with Loki.
- Yeah, get in line.
- Save it.
Save it. Loki's gonna keep this fight focused on us and that's
what we need. Without him these things could run wild.
We got Stark up top, he's gonna need us...
So, this all seems horrible.
- I've seen worse.
- Sorry.
No, we could use a little worse.
- Stark, we got him,
- Banne.
-  just like you said.
- Tell him to suit up. I'm bringing the party to you.
I don't see how that's a party.
Dr. Banner,
Dr. Banner, now might be a good time for you to get angry.
That's my secret, Captain.
I'm always angry.
Hold on.
Send the rest.
Guys.
- Call it, Captain.
Alright, listen up.
Until we can close that portal up there,
we're gonna use containment.
Barton, I want you on that roof, eyes on everything.
Call out patterns and strays.
Stark, you got the perimeter.
Anything gets more than three blocks out,
you turn it back or your turn it to ash.
- Wanna give me a lift?
- Right. Better clench up, Legoolas.
Thor, you've gotta try and bottleneck
that portal, slow them down.
You've got the lightning, light the bastards up.
You and me, we stay here on the
ground, keep the fighting here.
And Hulk,
Smash.
Sir.
Stark, you have a lot of
Strand out here.
- I try to keep them off the streets.
- But they cant bang with the them.
- Find the ....
- I will roger that.
Oh, boy.
Nice call, what else do you got?
We force taking out the squadron on 6.
And it didn't invite me.
Captain, none of this is gonna mean a
damn thing if we don't close that portal.
- Our biggest guns couldn't touch it.
- Well, maybe it's not about guns
You wanna get up there,
you're gonna need a ride.
I could use a boost though.
- You sure about this?
- Yeah, it's gonna be fun.
Turn, turn.
This way.
Director Fury, the council has made a decision.
I recognize the council has made a decision,
but given that it's a stupid assed decision,
I've elected to ignore it.
Director, you're closer than any of our subs,
you scramble that jet
That is the island of Manhattan, Councilman.
Until I'm certain my team can't hold it,
I will not order a nuclear strike
against a civilian population.
If we don't hold them in the air,
we lose everything.
I'd send that bird out, we already have.
Hawkeye.
- Nat, what are you doing?
- Little help.
I got him.
Enough!
You are all of you beneath me!
I am God, you dull creature,
and I will not be bullied by.
Puny God.
Doctor.
Loki's scepter, the energy...
the Tesseract can't fight.
You can't protect against yourself.
It's not your fault. You didn't know what you were doing.
Well, actually I think I did.
I built in a safety to cut the power source.
- Loki's scepter.
- It may be able to close the portal.
And I'm looking right at it.
Sir, we're losing power before penetrate that shell.
JARVIS, you hear
the Tell of Jonah?
I'm considering be a role model.
Director of Fury no longer responsible.
overwrite order 7-Alfa-1-1.
7-Alfa 1-1-confirmed.
We are about to take off.
Sir we have born in motion.
Anyone on the deck?
We need to shut it down.
I repeat, take off is not authorized.
Stark, do you hear me?
We have a missile headed straight for the city.
- How long?
- Three minutes, at best.
Stay load and wipe out them.
- Jarvis, put anything we got it.
- I just did.
The package is set. detonation in two
minutes and thirty seconds from now.
You ready for another bout?
What, you gettin' sleepy?
Right of to the front.
I can close it! Can anybody copy?
- I can shut the portal down!
- Do it!
- No, wait!
- Stark, these things are still coming!
I got a nuke coming in,
it's gonna blow in less than a minute.
And I know just where to put it.
Stark, you know that's a one way trip.
- Save the rest for the turn jarvs.
- Shall I tray Miss Potts?
- Where her?
New York streets
has become a battleground.
The army is here, and try to contain
violence, but clearly
But the billionaire
Iron Man, Tony Stark ...
Come on, Stark.
Close it.
Son of a guy.
He's not slowing down.
What the hell?
What just happened?
Please tell me nobody kissed me?
We won.
Alright. Hey. Alright. Good job
guys. Let's just not come in tomorrow.
Let's just take a day.
Have you ever tried shawarma?
There's a shawarma joint
about two blocks from here.
I don't know what it is, but I wanna try it.
We're not finished yet.
And then shawarma after.
If it's all the same to you,
I'll have that drink now.
This point of devastation
what has been confirmed...
...as extra terrestrial attack
be a extraordinary a heroic group
...known as The Avengers has been.....
I love you, Thor!
Super hero in New York?
Give me a break!
These so called heroes have to be held responsible
for the destruction done to the city.
This was their fight. Where are they now?
Captain America saved my life.
Whatever he is
and whatever any of them are i just
just want a say thank you.
- Where are the Avengers?
- I'm not currently tracking their whereabouts.
I'd say they'd earned a leave of absence.
- And the Tesseract?
- The Tesseract is where it belongs,
Out of our reach.
That's not your call.
I didn't make it.
So you let him take it and the war criminal, Loki,
who should be answering for his crime.
Oh, I think he will be.
I don't think you understand what you've started,
letting in The Avengers loose on some this world.
- They dangerous.
- They surely are,
and the whole world knows it. Every world knows it.
Was that the point in all this? A statement.
A promise.
How does it work now?
They've gone their separate ways,
some pretty extremely far.
We get into a situation like this again,
what happens then?
They'll come back.
- Are you really sure about that?
- I am.
- Why?
- Because we'll need them to.